<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="css/docbook.css"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>jXABSL Engine Tutorial</title>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Moritz</firstname>
                <surname>Wissenbach</surname>
            </personname>
            <email>m.wissenbach@stud.tu-darmstadt.de</email>
        </author>
    </info>
    <sect1>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>This tutorial briefy describes how to use the Java implementation of XABSL. XABSL is a
            language to specify the behavior of autonomous agents, utilizing a hierarchical state
            machine. Learn more about XABSL at <link>http://www.xabsl.de</link></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>General Sequence</title>

        <para>
            <simplelist>
                <member> Input/output symbols and basic behaviors specified in the XABSL source are
                    to be implemented in native Java.</member>
                <member> Those symbols and behaviors are then registered with the engine. </member>
                <member> The XABSL source is compiled to intermediate code and read in by the engine
                    to create the option graph.</member>
                <member> A step can now executed by calling <code>Engine.execute()</code></member>
            </simplelist>
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Reflection Engine</title>
        <para>When using the basic engine <code>de.xabsl.jxabsl.engine.Engine</code>, you have to
            implement and register all the input/output symbols and basic behaviors by hand (see
            below). To save you that work, there is
            <code>de.xabsl.jxabslx.engine.ReflectionEngine</code>, an extension of the basic engine.
            Say you have an object <code>agent</code> which contains methods and fields that you
            want to use as symbols/behaviors. You can then instantiate the engine with the agent
            object:
            <programlisting>
            Engine engine = new ReflectionEngine(debug, timeFunction, agent);
            </programlisting>
            Provided that the functions and fields are named appropriately, you can now simply
            construct the option graph, and the engine will register all symbols/behaviors on
            itself:
            <programlisting>
            File intermediateCode = new File("xabslsrc/intermediatecode");
                
            InputSource input;
                
            try {
                
                input = new ScannerInputSource(intermediateCode);
                engine.createOptionGraph(input);
                
             } catch (FileNotFoundException e) {
                e.printStackTrace();
             } catch (IntermediateCodeMalformedException e) {
                e.printStackTrace();
             }
            </programlisting>
            The engine will only look for symbols/behaviors that have not yet been registered
            manually. For any missing input- or output symbol <code>foo</code> the engine will look
            for the following, in this order: <simplelist>
                <member> Getter-/setter methods, i.e. methods that have the name <code>foo</code> /
                        <code> getFoo</code> or <code> setFoo</code>. Parameter list must match. One
                    and only one method must match, or the engine will issue an error</member>
                <member> A publicly accessible field <code>foo</code></member>
            </simplelist> As output symbols in XABSL are readable, there must be a way to obtain a
            value for each output symbol (for instance, a getter method). For any missing basic
            behavior <code>foo</code>, the engine will look for a method called <code> foo </code>
            with an appropriate parameter list. One and only one method must match, or the engine
            will issue an error. </para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Types</title>
            <para>By default, Java numerical types such as int, decimal etc. are mapped to XABSL
                decimal, Java boolean is mapped to boolean, and Java enum is mapped to enumerated.
                The ReflectionEngine will find public enums defined in the agent object.</para>
            <para>If you want to configure other types, have a look at
                    <code>de.xabsl.jxabslx.conversions.Conversions</code></para>
        </sect2>
        <title>Parameters</title>
        <para>Unfortunately, in Java methods, parameters are only identified by their position in
            the parameter list (but not by their name). In XABSL, on the other hand, parameters are
            identified by their name (but not their position). </para>
        <para>Thus, if there is a XABSL input symbol foo (float a, float b) and a Java function foo
            (float, float), the engine has no way of determining how to map the parameters. There
            are two ways to solve this problem: <simplelist>
                <member>Register the symbol manually.</member>
                <member>Enable parameter sorting, for example:
                        <code>engine.setParameterOrder(String.CASE_INSENSITIVE_ORDER);</code> The
                    engine will then map the lexical order of parameters to their position in
                    functions. You have to enable this manually to prove you know what you are
                    doing. </member>
            </simplelist></para>
        <sect2/>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Basic Engine</title>
        <para>The <code>ReflectionEngine</code> is in package <code>de.xabsl.jxabslx</code>. This
            package contains convenience classes and implementations. The basic engine is in package
                <code>de.xabsl.jxabsl</code>. None of the classes in this package depends on
                <code>xabslx</code>, so you can always use the bare engine implementation on its
            own. </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1><title>Examples</title> If you need more examples, look into the test cases that come
        with the engine. There is also an example application of the engine which lets a XABSL
        controlled team compete in a soccer match of the <code>TeamBots</code> environment.</sect1>
</article>
